<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to a question of a gentleman of quality (proposed to and made by a reverend and learned divine living in London) concerning the settlement or abolition of tithes by Parliament ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3341B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895553</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75411)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2341:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to a question of a gentleman of quality (proposed to and made by a reverend and learned divine living in London) concerning the settlement or abolition of tithes by Parliament ...</title>
                  <author>Spelman, Henry, Sir, 1564?-1641. Tithes too hot to be touched.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Philemon Stephens ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing S4931.</note>
                  <note>From a dis-bound copy of Tithes too hot to be touched (Wing S4931)?</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153039:1"/>
            <head>An anſwer to a queſtion of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of quality (propoſed to and made by a Reverend and learned Divine living in <hi>London</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſettlement or abolition of Tithes by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which cauſed him to doubt how to diſpoſe of his Sonne whom he had deſigned for the Miniſtrey: wherein alſo are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed ſome Animadverſions upon a late little pamphlet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Countryes plea againſt Tithes,</hi> diſcovering the ignorant miſtakings of the Authors of it, touching the maintenance of the Miniſtery.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough it were high preſumption for a private man, as I am, to preſage what ſo wiſe a Senate as the Parliament will doe for the future, either in point of Tithes, or any other affaire of ſo publike concernment, yet I hope I may, without reaching above my line, take upon me to tell you, that the ground of your doubt touching their alienation of Tithes from the Miniſtery, (which I ſhall bring in its proper place) is but ſuch as will ſerve rather to beare up a tranſient ſuſpicion or ſurmiſe of ſuch a matter, then a ſettled aſſurance that it either is ſo already, or that hereafter it will be ſo. For the firſt, <hi>That it is not ſo,</hi> I am ſure; becauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They have paſſed an Ordinance for the Miniſters recovery of Tithes, and other Miniſteriall dues from ſuch as doe detaine them, November 8. 1644. which is ſtill in force, through the influence of their power and favour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They have made competent additions to very many livings out of impropriated Tithes in the hands of Delinquents; and this they have done with ſo much cheerefulneſſe, and beneficence on the Miniſters behalfe, by the Committee for plundred Miniſters, that many have cauſe to bleſſe God for them as their great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and benefactors for that manner of maintenance; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they have done beyond and above any Parliament that were
<pb facs="tcp:153039:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153039:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153039:3"/>before them, and they continue and perſiſt in the making of ſuch augmentations, as occaſion is offered, to this very day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have given the repulſe to divers petitions againſt Tithes, which by the inſtinct and inſtigation of men of unſound princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and unquiet ſpirits have been put up unto them.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, that they will not take them away in time to come, I have theſe grounds, if not of infallible certainty, yet of very great probability.</p>
            <p>Though they have reſolved upon the ſale of Biſhops lands and revenues, in their Ordinance of November 16. 1646. for that purpoſe, they have made an eſpeciall exception with reſpect to the maintenance of Miniſters in theſe words, <hi>Except parſonages appropriate, tithes, tithes appropriate, oblations, obventions, por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of tithes, parſonages, vicarages, Churches, Chappels, advow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, donatives, nomination, rights of patronage and preſentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In excepting the right of patronage, they meane neither to leave it to the power of the people to chooſe what Miniſter they pleaſe, (and the practice of the Honourable Committee for plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miniſters ſheweth the ſame, for they appoint and place Miniſters very often without the petitions of the people, and ſometimes againſt them, as their wiſedome ſeeth cauſe; and if it were not ſo, many would chooſe ſuch as deſerved to be put out againe.) Nor to put the Miniſters upon the voluntary penſions, or contributions of the people for their ſubſiſtence, but aſſigne them under ſuch a title what belongeth unto them by the Laws of the Land, <hi>viz.</hi> Tithes, obventions, &amp;c. which intimates their mind not onely for the preſent, but for the future.</p>
            <p>Their wiſedome well knoweth that the Revenue of Tithes as it is moſt ancient for the originall of it, and moſt generall in practice, both for times and places, ſo it hath the beſt warrant from the word of God (not onely in the old Teſtament, which none can deny, but in the new, which though it be denyed by ſome, is averred by others, as D. <hi>Carleton,</hi> M. <hi>Roberts,</hi> D. <hi>Sclater,</hi> M. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> in their treatiſes of Tithes, and yet unrefuted by any) and from the Laws of many Chriſtian States, eſpecially from the Statutes of our Kingdome, whereof abundant evidence is given in the booke of the learned Antiquary, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Spelman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That notwithſtanding all the authority that may be pleaded
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153039:3"/>for them, the people are backward enough to pay to their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters a competent maintenance; and if Tithes ſhould be put down by the Parliament, it would be very much adoe to bring them up any other way to any reaſonable proportion of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for their ſupport; and ſo in moſt places the Miniſtery would be reduced to extreame poverty, and that poverty would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce contempt of their calling, and that contempt atheiſme.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is evident that ſuch as make the loudeſt noyſe againſt the tenure of Tithes, are as oppoſite to the office and calling of Miniſters as to their maintenance; and intend by their left<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed Logicke (becauſe as the ſaying is, the Benefit or Benefice is allotted to the office) to make way for the taking away of the Miniſtery, by the taking away of Tithes; and nor to wait the leiſure of conſequentiall operation, (according to the craft of <hi>Julian,</hi> who robbed the Church of meanes, expecting the want of wages would in time bring after it a want of workmen) but preſently to beare down both, as Relatives mutually inferre one another, as well by a negative as a poſitive inference; and ſo as the Parliament having put down the office of the Prelacy, now makes ſale of their lands, they, if they could prevaile for the diſcarding of Tithes, would by the ſame argument (cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and ſlander) preſently and importunately preſſe for depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Miniſtery. And we ſee how they take upon them with equall confidence and diligence, not onely to write, but <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Erbury</hi> at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford and <hi>Cox</hi> at London.</note> publikely to diſpute againſt them both.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That if rights, ſo firmely ſet upon ſo many ſolid foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould be ſupplanted, it would much weaken the tenure or title that any man hath to his lands, or goods, and would be a ready plea for raſh innovators; and the rather, becauſe of the manner of the Anabaptiſts proceedings, who began their claime of Chriſtian liberty with a <note n="b" place="margin">Sleydan Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. l. 5. fol. 71. a.</note> relaxation <hi>of Tithes,</hi> and went on to take off the Interdict or reſtraint in <hi>hunting, fiſhing,</hi> and <hi>fowling,</hi> wherein they would allow neither Nobility, nor Gentry, any more priviledge then the meaneſt peaſant. And as their principles were looſe; ſo were their practices licentious, for they held a <note n="c" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>community of goods, and equality of eſtates; <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonorum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> communione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; humanitati cum primis eſſe conſentaneam, &amp; ut ex digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aequales, &amp; ex conditione li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere &amp; promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuè omnibus bonis utuntur.</hi> Ibid. fol. 64. <hi>prope finem.</hi>
                  </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon</hi> the <hi>Common people gave over their worke, and whatſoever <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quo factum eſt, ut vulgus ab operis at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore deſiſteret, &amp; quâ quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> re careret ab aliis qui abundatant etiam invitis acciperit.</hi> Ibid. See alſo l. 10. <hi>princip.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153039:4"/>they wanted they tooke from the rich even againſt their good wills;</hi> So that it was a breach of their Chriſtian liberty, belike, to have a lock or a bolt on a doore, to keep a peculiar poſſeſſion of any thing from them. And the liberty was more and more amplified, according to the fancies of their dreaming doctors, for their dreames were the oracles of their common people; and every day they ſet forth their liberty in a new edition, <hi>corrupted and augmented,</hi> till all the partition walls of propriety were broken down; and ſo not content to have other mens goods at their diſpoſall, and to be quit from payment of rents, and debts, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made a monopoly of Saintſhip to themſelves) they excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated all who were not of their faction both out of ſacred ſociety of the Church, and out of common communion in the world as wicked and profane, and unworthy not onely of live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood but of life alſo; and uſurped a power to <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Promittebat auxilium quo</hi> viz. <hi>impiis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectis, novi ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituerentur principes &amp; Magiſtratus: namà Deo fibi mandatum eſſe profitebatur (ſcil.</hi> Munce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus) <hi>ut ſublatis illis conſtitueret novos</hi> Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>depoſe Prince and other Civill Magiſtrates, as they pretended they had commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to kill them, and to conſtitute new ones in their ſtead as they ſhould thinke fit. <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sathanas ſub Evangelii prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textu multos hoc temporeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioſos &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè ſanguinarios excitavit Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> Sleydan Comment: l. 5. fol. 72. See more of their Doctrine l. 10. <hi>principio.</hi> and of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Author of the ſame booke.</note> Such ſeditious and ſanguinary Doctors,</hi> as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> called them, <hi>did Satan ſtirre up under the pretext of Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall liberty;</hi> a liberty which in them admitted of no bounds, being like the &amp;c. oath without bankes, or bottome, of no rule or order, being carried on with a wild and giddy violence; ſuch as the great and pernicious impoſtor of the world prompted them unto, though they vented their diabolicall illuſions under the Title of Divine Revelations, as the Prince of darkneſſe made them believe, when he put on his holy-day habit, the appearance of an Angel of light. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the payment of Tithes where there are the fruits of the earth, and increaſe of cattell, out of which they may be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is the moſt equitable way and meanes of maintaining the Miniſter, ſince ſuch a gaine is not onely harmeleſſe, and without ſinne, for the manner of acquiſition, (which we cannot ſay of penſions and exhibitions made up out of trade or traffique) but ſuch as may be moſt permanent and conſtant, ſince whether the Tithe be leſſe or more, it is ſtill proportionable to the other nine parts; and if the yeares be plentifull, there is the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for houſe-keeping, if ſcarce, that part though leſſe is the more in price and worth, either for uſe in kind, or for exchange
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153039:4"/>for other commodities. Whereas a rate in money which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent in ſome places, and at ſome times, is incompetent in others, ſuch is the change both of monies and neceſſaries bought with money. For money, the time was <hi>when</hi> an ounce of ſilver now at 5. s. was valued but at 20. d. So in the Act of Parliament in the third of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, <hi>Cokes</hi> Inſtit. part 2. p. 410. <hi>when</hi> 20 markes a year was enough honourably to maintaine a Student at the Innes of Court. <hi>Forteſcue</hi> is his Commentary on the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> c. 49. p. 114. And this was held ſo great a charge as was to be borne onely by the ſonnes of Noblemen, and therefore they onely, ſaith the ſame Author, ſtudyed the Lawes in thoſe Innes, <hi>Ibid.</hi> And of old the Revenues fit for a Knight was rated to 20. l. a yeare, of a Baron to 400 markes a year, and of an Earle 400. l. a year: <hi>Cokes</hi> Inſtit. l. 2. c. 3. Sect. 95. fol. 69. and <hi>Lindwood</hi> in his provinciall Conſtitutions notes upon the rate of a Vicarage (for ſuch by the fraud and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of the ſuperior Popiſh Cleargy <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vicario per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum ſtipendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum ſtatuitur, niſi in partibus aliquibus Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae ubi minore contenti ſintd.</hi> Lindwood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. l. 1. <hi>de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. vicar.</hi> fol. 46. p. 2 col. 2. in Textu &amp; fol. 47. p. col. 1. <hi>Sed in gloſ. lit.</hi> g. <hi>Augmentatio facta eſt ad</hi> 8 <hi>Marcas, ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alii qui non ſunt contenti ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne decem Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis; &amp; revera</hi> 5 <hi>Marcae non ſufficiunt ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitalitatem &amp; alia</hi> Ibid. in gloſ. lit. g.</note> were many times deprived of Tithes, and put to penſions) that it was to be 5 marks in <hi>England,</hi> but in ſome parts of <hi>Wales</hi> they were content with leſſe, afterwards their meanes was augmented to 8 markes a year, but ſome would not be contented with leſſe then 10 marks a year; and, indeed ſaith the Gloſſe, 5 markes was too little for Hoſpitality, and other expences; implying that 10 markes was ſufficient for all occaſions.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As for money, ſo for commodities to be bought with it, the prices have been very various; In the <note n="b" place="margin">See Polt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg. Edict. Londin. 1640. p. 11.</note> Statute entituled <hi>Aſſiſa pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; cerviſiae,</hi> made Anno 51 <hi>H.</hi> 3. and Anno Dom. 1266. the deareſt rate for a quarter of wheate (which in the middle of the Kingdome is a meaſure containing eight times four peckes, I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it by that proportion, becauſe it is more generally knowne) was 12. s. the cheapeſt 1. s. ſo that betwixt theſe two extreames the ordinary rate might be about 6. s. the quarter. And for other proviſions the rate ſet upon them in a dearth in the Reigne of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond was this, <hi>for an oxe fatted with graſſe fifteene ſhillings, for one fatted with corn twenty ſhillings; the beſt cow twelve ſhillings, a fat hogge of two yeares old three ſhillings; a fat ſheep ſhorne fourteen pence, with the fleece twenty pence; a fat gooſe two pence halfepenny, a fat capon two pence halfepenny, a fat henne a peny,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153039:5"/>four pigeons a peny, ſo that whoſoever ſold above ſhould forfeit their ware to the King.</hi> Dan. Hiſt. l. 2. p. 209. And I well remember that not very many yeares agoe there was a controverſie brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the commiſſioners of charitable uſes in Cheſhire; wherein was diſcovered the cheapneſſe of things in former times: the caſe was thus. There was a legacy of twenty markes given to the pariſh of Wood-church in that County to buy oxen to till the ground of poore men, with which ſmall ſumme at the time of the dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (about ſevenſcore yeares before) were bought no fewer then twenty yoke of oxen; which becauſe the poore people were not able ſo to keep that they might be ſtrong to labour, it was thought fit to ſell them and to buy in their ſtead as many milch kine as the mony would reach unto, which were to be hired at a low rate to ſuch as were not able to buy ſuch cattell for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But it is yet a cheaper price we read of in <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt his dayes, when by <hi>Stat. Weſtm.</hi> an oxe was to be ſold but at 5. s. ſo in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 1. cited in <hi>Cokes</hi> Inſtit. part 2. p. 410. How rates are raiſed in the preſent age (whether by ſcarcity of things, or by the increaſe of people, or multiplication of coyne, or all) is not unknowne to any, and too much experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally by many whoſe portion is too penurious for their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary expences. Nor is this great difference of rates, either for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or for goods, brought to paſſe on the ſodaine, but raiſed by degrees; ſo that if the rule of tithing ſhould be laid down, the Miniſters wages muſt be changed, as <hi>Jacobs</hi> was in <hi>Labans</hi> ſervice, many times over, which would be an intricate trouble to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to ſeverall variations of perſons, and places; to which inconvenience the maintenance by Tithes is not obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; nor to any other, which may be compared with ſuch as will hardly be ſeparated (if at all) from the alienation of Tithes.</p>
            <p>That if any innovation be made in this matter, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be diſpleaſed with it, (as they will quickly be diſpleaſed with any thing which puts them to coſt) they will take the more boldneſſe to contemne it, becauſe it is new, and for that it neither hath, nor is like to have ſuch a ratification of authority, either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or humane, by conſtitution or preſcription, as tithing hath had; no, though it ſhould be ſuppoſed to laſt to the end of the world. For Tithes were paid 1933 yeares, almoſt 2000 yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153039:5"/>Chriſt; <hi>Salian</hi> Annal. <hi>Tom</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 251. <hi>nu.</hi> 41. &amp; ſince Chriſt (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſome times of perſecution) for the moſt part of ſixteene hundred fourty ſixe yeares; and we cannot hope the remaining age of the world will hold out halfe ſo long.</p>
            <p>To theſe I could adde divers other conſiderations of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which cannot be hid from the prudence of ſuch a multitude of ſage Counſellors as that moſt Honourable Senate the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſiſteth of; which maketh me confident that before they give aſſent to any ſuch petitions as are put up againſt Tithes, they will be pleaſed to heare what the Aſſemblie of Divines can ſay in anſwer to ſuch objections, as are framed againſt them, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence either of Scripture or religious reaſon.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Animadverſions upon the Petition of the Committee of <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AGainſt this, that which moved you to thinke the Parliament would take away Tithes, was, that you have read in one of the newes bookes, that the Knights and Gentlemen of <hi>Kent</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented a petition to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, againſt the payment of Tithes unto Miniſters, and that they received thanks from the Speaker in the name of the Houſe for that ſervice, and that it is held fit to be a leading caſe for all other Counties of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>You muſt beware how you believe the newes bookes, for they are many times ignorantly and inconſiderately erroneous, or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laciouſly falſe, out of an ill affection to ſome, and apparent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality to others.</p>
               <p>For the Petition it ſelfe, 1. It commeth not as from the Knights and Gentlemen of that County in common, (who I am credibly informed are not very well pleaſed with it) but from the Committee of <hi>Kent,</hi> who (if they be like the Committees in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places) are not all of them men of ſound, and orthodox Judgement, neither for matter of Tithes, nor for divers other Tenets of Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Howſoever they profeſſe a good meaning to eſtabliſh a ſufficient maintenance <hi>for godly and well deſerving Miniſters;</hi> a very good meaning to extend it ſo farre as to ſuccor their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153039:6"/>do wes and fatherleſſe children, as we ſee by the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> propoſition of their new project. It will be a probleme (which the preſent age perhaps will not be able to reſolve) who the Truſties in after times will accept for ſuch Miniſters; although they may have cauſe to ſuſpect that ſome part of <hi>Kent</hi> for the preſent is not ſo refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as it ſhould be; Anabaptiſts and other ſectaries having miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many into adverſe principles, not onely to Tithes, but to other matters of moment, concerning mans duty both of the firſt and ſecond Table.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For their exceptions againſt the received maintenance by Tithes they ſay firſt, in generall, <hi>That they bewayle the ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Country, in reſpect of the uncertaine floting, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition of the Miniſtry, occaſioned by the very nature, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and adjuncts of the way of Tithes; which the experience of thus many ages doth plainly evince to be miſerably attended with theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing miſchiefes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer;</p>
               <p>That the miſerable and floting condition of the Miniſtry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from the nature, manner or adjuncts of their ſubſiſtence by way of Tithes; nor doth the experience of thus many ages (that is, of the precedent ages hitherto) evince ſo much; for God (who is omniſcient, and therefore cannot but foreſee all ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent inconveniences for many hundred yeares to come) eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that meanes to be a ſtanding and ſettled maintenance for his ſervice; and the miſery of the Miniſtry proceeds not from the nature or manner of Tithes (which to affirme may ſeem to coaſt too neere their conceipt who imagine God to be the author of ſinne) but from the ill conſciences of men, who make no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to rob God of his right, <hi>Malach.</hi> 3. (for Tithes are his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30.) and Miniſters may ſuffer very much in the preſent age, becauſe there be many Anabaptiſticall ſectaries (from which <hi>Kent</hi> is not more free, but as ſome ſay, more infected then ſome other Counties) who take up importunate clamours againſt Tithes as Antichriſtian and Jewiſh; and there will be the more by the countenance they may have from ſuch a petition; and ſuch petitioners, becauſe divers of them are of good reputation, not onely for wealth, but for their wiſedome and learning well affected to Religion and the Parliament; and I beleeve it the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153039:6"/>rather, becauſe ſome godly miniſters have expreſſed their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation both of it &amp; them, though therein I conceive they ſhewed more of the ſimplicity of the dove then of the wiſedome of the ſerpent; for albeit their meaning might be ſo to gather the Tithes, and to put them into ſuch hands, as might be rather for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters eaſe then for their loſſe, no man can propheſie that ſo good a ſpirit will deſcend upon their ſucceſſors, nor how croſſe they may prove to ſuch a Chriſtian Intention.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>
                  </label> 2. For the particular exceptions, they ſay; firſt, <hi>That for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this ſubſiſtence it is a very myſtery, and ſecret, not eaſily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much art and induſtry attained unto; namely for the Miniſter to know his dues demandable, or the pariſhioners their dues payable; whence ariſeth that multitude of ſcandalous and vexatious ſuites and brables betwixt Miniſters and people, which doth fill all the Courts at Weſtminſter, and other the Juſtice-ſittings in the Country like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with cauſes in this kinde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this charge there be two particulars contained, firſt, of the difficulty of knowing the right of Tithes; ſecondly, of the vexatious ſuites raiſed betwixt paſtors and people upon that ground.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, It is a very ſtrange myſtery, that after ſo many hundred yeares of Tithing it ſhould not yet be knowne what it is; but I doubt not but in this caſe the right is better knowne unto Miniſters that ſhould receive Tithes, then acknowledged by the people that ought to pay them; And how can they ſet up their new deſigne upon the old foundation of Tithing, as they project it, if it cannot be knowne what is the Miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandable due, what the peoples payable duty: that modell is more like to be a myſtery which they propound, ſince it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in this Kingdome untill they had deviſed it; and as like it is to prove a miſery to Miniſters, if their portion ſhould come into no better hands then moſt of theirs, who have petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned againſt Tithes ſince this Seſſion of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, for the multitude of ſcandalous and vexatious ſuites, they make no more againſt the Right of Tithes, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt borrowing and lending, buying and ſelling, letting of leaſes, ſetling inheritances, Joyntures, &amp;c. upon which titles are ſet the greateſt number of ſuites; and for ſuites for Tithes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153039:7"/>if the law allow them a right, it alloweth them a remedy to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that right; and for the ſuites that were occaſioned thereby, they are neither ſo many as is here preſented, nor ſo ſcandalous for the Miniſters part, for they may be imputed to the old avarice of worldly minded men, who being of a contrary mind to the Apoſtle, thinke it an hard bargaine <hi>to exchange their carnall for the Miniſters ſpirituall things;</hi> but principally to the new principles and practiſes of ſuch unreaſonable reformers, as imagine they are never farre enough removed from one extreame untill they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at the other, accounting all ſuperſtitious in point of Tithing, that are not ſacrilegious.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>
                  </label> 2. <hi>For the manner of it, reſpecting either the collecting or pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tithes, it is a mutuall ſcourge in the hand of Miniſters and people each to other, if either or both (as too often it happens) prove covetous or croſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> If it be a mutuall ſcourge, it would well become the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of theſe Committee-men to enquire where the right is, and who doth the wrong, and to project a way how the wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doer may be made to doe right and to give due ſatisfaction to ſuch as ſuffer under an undeſerved ſcourge, and I hope when our reformation is grown up to ſuch a competent degree of ſtrength and ſtature as that it may quit the ſervice of Country Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, there will be no more cauſe of ſuch a complaint then for many hundred yeares heretofore there hath been.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>
                  </label> 3. <hi>For its adjuncts (that is of the maintenance by Tithes) the miſchiefes of them will appeare innumerable, if the pregnancy of onely one be but conſidered; namely, in the unreaſonable proportion of livings, or values of Churches to which they are belonging, whence ariſe theſe inſeparable evils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> By what new-found Logick will you frame ſuch an Inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as from one particular to inferre innumerable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, particularly from the diſproportion of livings? You ſeeme to thinke otherwiſe, where you ſay in your 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>that in the diſtribution of the revenues for Miniſters regard muſt be had to the deſert of the perſon, his family, and charge;</hi> if ſo, certainly there is a great diſproportion in deſerts; and for charge it is conſiderable, not onely for the greatneſſe of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters family, but for the dearneſſe of his education; ſome have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153039:7"/>ſpent many yeares, and a large patrimony in the Univerſity, to make them fit for the Miniſtery; and ſhould not they be ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a more liberall allowance <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> then thoſe who have been at little expence both of time &amp; eſtate to be duely qualified for ſuch a calling? If the proportion of parts, and paines, of charge both Academicall, and Oeconomicall, be due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighed, there will be many more livings found too little then too great for a Miniſters maintenance; eſpecially if you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him a Library (ſuch as a learned Knight thought neceſſary for a Miniſter) of 600. l. value. But if the proportion be unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, muſt Tithes be ſupplanted and their ancient Tenure abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for ſuch a diſproportion? muſt the foundation be digged up becauſe the building is too high? may not a tree, whoſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are too luxuriant, be lopped, and left entire in the bodie and roote? when a mans beard is too long, will you cut off his chinne? that out of doubt were an unreaſonable reformation.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>
                  </label> 4. From this unreaſonable proportion, you ſay, ariſe theſe unſeparable evils. 1 <hi>That moſt unworthy perſons, who by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or friendſhip or any ſiniſter wayes can get into the greateſt livings, being once inveſted with a legall right of freehold for their lives, ſecurely fleece the flocke, and feed themſelves without feare or care, more then to keep themſelves without the compaſſe of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration, whilſt others both painfull and conſcionable both ſerve ſtarve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> This is not (as you call it) an unſeparable evill from the proportion you ſpeake of; for there be ſome men who have had, and at this preſent have great livings, not by any ſiniſter wayes, but by ſuch favour and friendſhip as is ingenuous, and juſt, and who keep as great a diſtance from deſert of ſequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as any Committee man doth within the County wherein they live. And if they carry themſelves ſo as to be without feare and care, and without the compaſſe of a ſequeſtration, in theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive and accuſative times, they are more to be countenanced and encouraged then many of thoſe who are profeſſed adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to them. But the matter, it ſeemes, that troubles you is, that <hi>they are inveſted with a legall right of freehold for their lives,</hi> and if they have ſuch a right, and walke ſo warily as to keep out of the reach of a juſt ſequeſtration, why ſhould they not enjoy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153039:8"/>it? would you have all to be betruſted to the diſcretion and conſcience of your arbitrary Committees? Truely Gentelemen, we are afraid to truſt you ſo farre, as to give up ſuch a certaine title as formerly and anciently eſtabliſhed upon the Incumbent by the fundamentall Lawes of the Land, as the right of any perſon to his Temporall eſtate, and to ſtand to your arbitrary diſpenſations for our livelihood; leſt <hi>Laban</hi>-like you ſhould change our <hi>wages ten times:</hi> and if your petition ſhould take place, it might prove of very ill conſequence in another generation, were you never ſo well minded, and it may be ſooner (in the next ſucceſſion:) for if the Truſtees ſhould be either proud or covetous, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane or licentious, hereticall, or ſchiſmaticall, the beſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters might happily be the worſt dealt withall; and the right of receiving Tithes taken out of their hands might put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the paſſive condition of filly and impotent wards under ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till and domineering <hi>Tutors</hi> or <hi>Guardians,</hi> in name <hi>ſuch,</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed nothing leſſe then aſſertors and defenders of their rights, as Tutors and Guardians ought to be. And that our feare and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie is not without cauſe in reſpect of Truſtees and Committee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor ſo much of you in particular, of ſome of whom we have heard and beleeve much good, as of ſuch as may have as great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority without ſo good an intention, we ſhall give you our ground out of the obſervation and complaint of witneſſes above exception, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>well affected freemen and covenant-engaged Citizens of the City of</hi> London, <hi>in their humble repreſentation to the right Honourable the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>And here we may not omit to hint unto your Honours the exorbitant practiſes of many Committees and Committee-men, who have ſuch an influence by meanes of their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon the people, they being at their wills and in their power to doe them a diſpleaſure, that they dare not doe otherwiſe, then obey their unlawfull commands, without the inevitable hazard of their peace and ſafety; through which meanes tyranny is exerciſed by one fellow-ſubject upon another, and juſtice and equity cannot enter. The cryes of all ſorts of people through the land are growne ſo loud againſt the people of this vocation and profeſſion, by reaſon of thoſe grievous oppreſſions that are continually acted by them, that in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of affection toward our brethren, not being ignorant or inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153039:8"/>of our owne ſufferings in this kind, and the great diſhonour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crewing to the Parliament thereby, that we cannot but be earneſt ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to your mercy and juſtice that ſuch may be diſſolved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>
                  </label> 2. For <hi>obtainment of theſe livings we ſee ſuch ſordid compliances with ſuch perſons as have the fatteſt benefices (as they count and call them) in their diſpoſe; ſuch artifices in contriving, making, and colouring over Simoniacall and ſinfull bargaines, compacts, and matches, ſuch chopping of Churches, and reſtleſſe change of places, till they get into the eaſieſt and warmeſt: and other ſuch like practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not to be named, nor yet to be prevented or removed, otherwiſe then by plucking up the very roote which naturally brancheth out it ſelfe into theſe foreſaid miſchiefes, ſo obſtructive and deſtructive to all reformation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Here is a great deale of aggravating rhetoricke againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Church-livings. But why ſhould all this evill be imagined rather of Miniſters fat benefices as you ſay they are called, then of great and gainfull offices in the State? Is there not more care had, and more ſtrict triall taken of Miniſters ſincerity and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity then of ſecular officers? ſurely we are bound in charity to expect a more reformed Miniſtery, then we have had, who will rather ſay unto a Simoniacall patron as <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus, Thy monie periſh with thee, Acts</hi> 8.20. then be <hi>Levies</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Simeon</hi> in making a baſe and corrupt contract for a benefice. And for that you ſay, that <hi>ſuch practiſes are not to be prevented or removed, otherwiſe then by plucking up the very roote, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally brancheth it ſelfe out into theſe foreſaid miſchiefes, ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and deſtructive to all religion.</hi> Whether you meane Tithes to be this roote, or the diſproportion of Benefices, or the right of patronage and protection, I cannot tell, but ſure I am, that the Apoſtle cals <hi>covetouſneſſe the root of all evill,</hi> and ſo the root of that evill which ſometimes paſſeth betwixt a Patron and his Chaplaine: and may as frequently, and with as much injury be found betwixt ſome Committee-men and Truſtees and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their choice, as any other. But as I am confident that there will be an amendment on the Miniſters part, by the regular way of the Parliaments reformation, according to the directions of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Miniſters already printed &amp; accordingly practiſed, ſo will it bee not onely poſſible, but eaſie for the State to finde out
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153039:9"/>a fit means to prevent prevarication on the part of the Patron; but if Tithes be removed from their ancient foundation, and leſt looſe to the diſpoſall of Truſtees or Committee-men, they will be a more ready prey for the covetous into whoſe hands they may come, and from whoſe hands perhaps they cannot without great difficulty be redeemed.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, in the cloſe of this Petition, the Petitioners ſhew great care that the Miniſters may be freed from the incumbrance of Tithes, <hi>to ſerve the Lord without diſtraction, and to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Word of God and Prayer, and to be onely employed to make ready a people prepared for the Lord;</hi> And ſo they may do if they be maintained by Tithes; for that means of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance gives a man occaſion of more and better acquaintance with the particular diſpoſition of his people, and it is his part to <hi>be diligent to know the ſtate of his flock, Prov.</hi> 27.23. And for that trouble which may be thought inconſiſtent with the Calling of a Miniſter, if his means be ſufficient, he may have a ſervant to take it from him, and eaſe him of it. I know a Miniſter whoſe Benefice was a Vicarage, and his Pariſh ſo large, that it was 11 miles in length, and of a proportionable breadth, yet did it not put him to the expence of one day in a year to compound for, or gather in his diſperſed portion.</p>
               <p>Now for the ſucceſſe and acceptance of the Petition in the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to which it was preſented; if ſuch an innovation had been granted for that County, it had been fitter to have been made a <hi>Sibboleth,</hi> for that <hi>cauthe</hi> or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of the Kingdome (for ſo the word <hi>Kent</hi> ſignifieth) as their cuſtome of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gavelkind</hi> is a cuſtome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Kent,</hi> whereby the land of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is equally divided among all his ſons, or the land of a brother equally divided among his brethren, if he have no iſſue of his own, this was ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a cuſtome as appears by the Stat. in the 18. year of <hi>H. 6. ca.</hi> 1. that there were not above 30 or 40 perſons in <hi>Kent</hi> that held by any other tenure; but <hi>Anno</hi> 31 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 3. many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon Petition got an alteration thereof.</note> 
                  <hi>Gavelkind,</hi> then to be made a preſident or pattern of conformity to other parts of the Kingdome, as the Newſ-Book of the ſame week preſcribed that to his Reader.</p>
               <p>But the anſwer of the worthy Senate was ſuch as may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirm us in our confidence, that they will ſtill continue to be gracious Patrons of the maintenance of Miniſters, and that they will be more ready to ratifie precedent Statutes and their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153039:9"/>own Ordinance made in that behalf, then to diſſettle their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure which is founded upon them, and to make Miniſters arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Penſioners to ſuch as may be ſo far ſwayed by miſpriſion of judgement, or perſonall diſ-affection, as to deal moſt penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly with thoſe, who being truly valued (without erroneous miſtaking or injurious miſliking) may both by the eminence of their parts, and their faithfulneſſe in their places, deſerve the moſt ample, and moſt honourable Revenue. I will give you their anſwer in their own words, which are moſt authentick, they are theſe.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Speaker by order of the Houſe of Commons did give the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners (the Committee of</hi> Kent) <hi>thanks for their former ſervices, and took notice of their good affections to the Publique; and did acquaint them, That the great buſineſſes of the Kingdome are now inſtant and preſſing upon them, and that they will take the Petition into conſideration in due time, and that in the mean time they take care that Tithes may be paid according to Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But there are ſome in the Parliament that hold the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Miniſters by Tithes to be Jewiſh and Popiſh, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will give countenance to Petitions that are put up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and doe what they can under ſuch titles to render them offenſive to ſuch as are truly religious, eſpecially to thoſe who have moſt power to aboliſh them.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. It may be there are ſome ſuch, and if there be ſome ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many, it is neither to be thought ſtrange, nor true, for ſuch a number of them as may be able to carry the cauſe againſt the continuance of Tithes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the tearm Jewiſh, it is miſ-applyed againſt Tithes, as it was by the Prelates of late, &amp; is by the Anabaptiſts at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent againſt the Sabbath; nor are they more Popiſh then Jewiſh; For the Papiſts, though their people pay them, and their Prieſts receive them, yet they for the moſt part holding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to depend meerly upon Eccleſiaſtical conſtitution, made no ſcruple of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them into ſecular titles or uſes, as in Impropriations in the hands of Lay-men, and many other diſtributions made out of them ſeverall ways, without any reſpect to the ſervice of the Sanctuary. Nor is there any thing in the payment and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Tithes under the ſtate of the Goſpel, which may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153039:10"/>be ſuſpected to have any ſavour of Judaiſme, or Popery, ſave onely the payment of Tenths by the Miniſters to the King, as hath been lately well obſerved by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>L.</hi> in his ſecond Book againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> I will ſet down his words, and ſeriouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to the conſideration of our religious Reformers; they are theſe, in anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> his Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Smoke p.</hi> 25.</note> are the maintenance of Miniſters by Tithes? Jewiſh and Popiſh undenyably.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. <hi>How? Jewiſh and Popiſh undeniably? As undeniably as the Sabbath was Jewiſh when the Prelates ſo called it, or the article of the Trinity Popiſh, as</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qued Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae reformatae ad huc in fide Tinitatis cum Papiſtis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniret. Bell. praefat. in lib. de Chriſte, Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ſecund Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſ. general. p.</hi> 271.</note> Valentinus Gentilis <hi>took it, when he diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the doctrine of the Reformed Churches in that point, becauſe they agreed with the Papiſts therein. You are groſſely miſtaken Sir in the tenure of Tithes, for though there be a clamour taken up againſt them by ſuch as make no ſcruple either of ſlander or of ſacriledge, and ſome would change the Miniſters portion, which is their maſters wages for his own work, and reduce them to volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary penſions of the people, (becauſe they would have a liberty to begger them who will not humour them in their fond and falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and licentious practiſes, but oppoſe them as of conſcience they are bound to doe) neither you, nor all your party can prove them either Iewiſh or Popiſh, as they are allowed and received for the maintenance of the Miniſters of</hi> England. <hi>And becauſe you are ſo confident in your opinion againſt Tithes, and ſhew your ſelf to have a good opinion of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Nye, (<hi>whom with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Goodwin <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Smoke p.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>you cite for a worthy ſaying touching the golden Ball of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) I refer you for ſatisfaction to him, who will tell you (as he hath done divers others in my hearing) that Miniſters of the Goſpel may hold, and receive Tithes for their maintenance by a right and title which is neither Jewiſh nor Popiſh, but truly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; and there is nothing Iewiſh or Popiſh in Tithes, but the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of the</hi> decimae decimarum, <hi>from the <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.28</note> Leviticall Prieſts to the high Prieſt, from the high Prieſt to the <note n="e" place="margin">
                        <hi>In veteri lege primitiae debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, decimae autem Levitis, &amp; quia ſub ſacerdotibus Levitae erant, Dominus man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit ut ipſi lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co decimarum ſolverent ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſacerdoti decimam deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, unde nunc eadem ratione tenentur Clerici ſummo pontifici decimam dare ſi exigeret. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 87. <hi>a.</hi> 4. <hi>ad.</hi> 3. <hi>Soto</hi> 9. <hi>Inſt. q.</hi> 4. <hi>art.</hi> 4. <hi>ad.</hi> 3. <hi>Lorin. in Num.</hi> 18.28. <hi>p.</hi> 687.</note> Pope, and from the Pope to the King; when firſt Pope</hi> Urbane <hi>gave them to</hi> Richard <hi>the ſecond to aid him againſt</hi> Charles <hi>the French King, and others that upheld</hi> Clement <hi>the ſeventh againſt him, as</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Polyd. Virg. Hiſt. l.</hi> 16.</note> Polydore Virgil <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth. And King</hi> Henry <hi>the eighth taking from the Pope the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of head of the Church to himſelf by <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Poult. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg. p.</hi> 561.</note> Act of Parliament, took
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153039:10"/>from him the tenths, and other profits annexed to that title, which were ſetled upon the Crown by <note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 565.</note> Statute in the</hi> 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>year of</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8. <hi>ſo that the Iewiſh high Prieſthood being expired, the papall Lordſhip aboliſhed, the Tithes paid under thoſe titles, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iewiſh and Popiſh, but not that which is aſſigned for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Miniſters, becauſe they are yet to doe ſervice to their Maſter, and ſo to receive the maintenance of his allowance for his work; which fellow-ſervants cannot take upon them to take away without preſumption; their door-neighbour will not allow them a power to appoint the wages of their ſervants, much leſſe may they uſurp upon the right of God, and his Miniſters, to alienate tithes from the ſupport of his ſervice and worſhip, for that is rather Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, as hath before been obſerved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which being true and clear, (as touching the pedegree of ſuch Tithes from the high Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> to the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prelacy of the Pope, and from him to the King, as by claim from the title, <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> tranſlated from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Crown) it will not I conceive be thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous to the Chriſtian Reformation (the thorow Reformation profeſſed by our worthy and religious Rulers) that ſuch Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Superſtition or Popery ſhould be removed, which were unprofitable, and that onely retained (as a ſilver ſhrine to <hi>Diana</hi>) which brings gain to the King or State, and puts the charge upon the Miniſters of the Goſpel; who thereby (I may ſay it confidently for ſome whom I know) are brought to this perplexed <hi>Dilemma,</hi> either to pay them with reluctancy, (as no leſſe contrary to their conſciences then to their commodities) or to deny or withhold them with ſuſpition, or imputation of avarice, or diſobedience to lawfull Authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> But the Parliament liketh not that Tithes ſhould be propoſed, or preſſed, as many Divines doe, both in Pulpit, and from the Preſſe, as of divine right; which becauſe they think to be wrong, they will rather reject them, then ratifie them under a title of ſo high a ſtrain.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. Not onely Divines, but divers <note n="i" place="margin">Sir. <hi>Ed. Coke</hi> in his ſecond Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the Archb: of Can. his caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 49. <hi>b.</hi> And ſo the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the foregoing lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Work.</note> others (who are men of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eminent note) hold Tithes to be due by divine right, and ſome of them have undertaken to prove them ſo, and to anſwer all objections againſt them, which how far they have performed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153039:11"/>is left to the judgement of indifferent Readers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is more like that (as both religion and reaſon will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate unto them) they will be the more wary how they take them away, leſt if that tenure ſhould prove true, they ſhould be found guilty of the ſin of ſacriledge, that they ſhould aboliſh them, and that they will ſeriouſly ſearch and enquire into the ground of that title, and while they are in doubt, that they will reſolve of the ſafeſt courſe, which is, not to repeal them; for as we muſt forbear to feed of meats of which another ſaith, that they are <hi>ſacrificed to idols,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.28. (for his ſake that ſaith it, though but a private Chriſtian;) ſo if Divines ſay, (and bring Scripture and reaſon for it) that Tithes are dedicated to God, or by him aſſumed, firſt to himſelf, and then aſſigned or ſet over by him to his ſervants, for his work in waiting on his worſhip, which muſt be maintained to the worlds end, it will be rather a reaſon for them to ſupport the tenure of Tithes by their Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentary power, then any way to prompt or diſpoſe them to deſert it, or to alienate their right from Eccleſiaſticall uſes.</p>
               <p>The fear of ſacriledge hath been of ſuch force with ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Moraliſts, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> obſerveth in his Morals, that if they pulled down a houſe contiguous to a temple, they would leave ſome of that part ſtanding which was next unto it, leſt they ſhould with it take away any part of the Temple it ſelfe. Wherein if they ſhewed any ſpice of ſuperſtition, it will be more capable of pardon, or leſſe liable to puniſhment at the hand of God, then we may expect if we proceed haſtily to lay violent hands upon any thing peculiarly entituled to his honour, who is the authour and giver of all things to all men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the plea of a divine right for Tithes (ſuppoſing it ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them up too high) ſhould incline to irritation in ſome to make oppoſition againſt them, why ſhould not the contrary te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net which peremptorily taketh them down too low, calling them Jewiſh, Antichriſtian, and Popiſh, and that undeniably, (as hath been ſaid, but never can be proved) move others the rather to retaine them, and confirm them? chiefly the Parliament (whoſe authority is moſt engaged for their juſtification) and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince the ſervants of God have had poſſeſſion of them by ſo many laws, and ſo long a preſcription; for according to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153039:11"/>the maxime of the law, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Longa poſſeſſio (ſicut jus) parit jus poſſidendi &amp; tollit actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vero domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> Bract. l. 2. fo. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>the poſſeſſers title is the beſt untill he bee fairly evicted out of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Parliament doe not in their approbation of Tithes come up to the tenure of divine right, they may yet be willing enough to eſtabliſh them upon other grounds, and leave Divines to the liberty of their judgment &amp; conſciences to plead for them according to the principles of their own profeſſion, as in their Ordinances made for ſetting up of the Presbyterial Government, though yet they be not ſatisfied of the claim of divine right for it, they were pleaſed to authorize it by their Ordinance, and to require Divines to prepare the people for the reception there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by preaching of it, and for it; ſo as both to clear it, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it (ſo farre as they could) by the ſacred Scripture.</p>
               <p>And on the other ſide while they approve it, though but by a civill aſſent, (as to a prudentiall deſign, untill they ſee more light, which they look for in the Anſwer to their Queres propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Aſſembly of Divines) the Presbyterians who hold it in the higheſt eſteem take none offence that they proceed no farther, and profeſſe themſelves well ſatisfied with their civill ſanction; ſo one of the learned Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath ſaid, in the name of the reſt, in theſe words. <note place="margin">M. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi> his brotherly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of M. <hi>Colemans</hi> Serm. <hi>p.</hi> 32, 33.</note> 
                  <hi>If they ſhall in a Parliamentary and Legiſlative way eſtabliſh that thing, which is really, and in it ſelf agreeable to the Word of God, though they doe not declare it to be the will of Ieſus Chriſt, they are ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> If there were no purpoſe to put down Tithes by ſuch as are in Authority, how commeth it to paſſe that the Anabaptiſts are more bold in <hi>London</hi> to take up a publique conteſtation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, then the Presbyterians to make apology for them? for did not one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B. C.</hi> an Anabaptiſt manage a diſpute againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>W. I.</hi> of Chr. and after that undertake another upon the ſame argument againſt M. <hi>I. Cr.</hi> and offered to proceed in it againſt all oppoſition, which M. <hi>Cr.</hi> durſt not doe, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a prohibition from authority?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is no ſtrange thing for men who have a bad cauſe to ſet a good face on it, and to make out with boldneſſe and confidence what is wanting in truth of judgement, and ſtrength of argument; <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Ed: Sands Europ. Specul. p.</hi> 85.</note> this is obſerved of the Papiſts by a judicious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, whom he ſheweth to have been forward in the <hi>offers of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputation;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153039:12"/>with iterated and importunate ſuits for publique audience and judgement.</hi> And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> reporteth out of <hi>Surius,</hi> that <hi>Io: Cochlens</hi> a great Zealot for the Papacy, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obtulit ſe ad diſputandum cum quovis Lutherano ſub poena capitis ſi in probationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus defeciſſet.</hi> Bell. de Eccleſ. Script. p. 423.</note> offered <hi>to diſpute with any Luther an upon perill of his life, if he fayled in the proof of his part of the Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For the boldneſſe of the Anabaptiſts at this time, and in this Cauſe, and this City, there may be divers conjectural reaſons in particular given thereof, beſides the generall already obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe they advance in their hopes of a toleration of their Sect; and to promote that hope they have been ſo ready to engage in military ſervice, with a deſigne no doubt to get that liberty by force (if they be able) which by favour of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they cannot obtain.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For this matter of Tithes, they might be more forward to oppoſe their tenure, becauſe it is a very popular and plauſible argument, wherein they might have the good wils of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they might prevail, and their conceits that they did ſo, <note place="margin">Quod valdè volumus facilè credimus.</note> (though they did not) becauſe they would <hi>be very apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve what they vehemently deſire may come to paſſe;</hi> and it is not to be doubted but a dram of ſeeming probability will prevail more with moſt worldlings to ſpare their purſes, then an ounce of ſound reaſon to put them to charges.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They might take ſome encouragement to diſpute againſt Tithes in this City, becauſe there is a project to change the maintenance of the Miniſters ſet on foot by many worthy, and well-minded Citizens, which yet in truth makes nothing for the Anabaptiſts opinion, who would have Miniſters maintained by meer benevolence; for the Citizens, as they intend a more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall allowance then the former, (ſince they ſee many of their Churches are deſtitute of Miniſters, becauſe their Miniſters have been deſtitute of means) ſo they mean that it ſhall be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſetled by Authority, and not left arbitrary to the courteſie of men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the two diſputes, the one managed betwixt M. <hi>W. I.</hi> and M. <hi>B. C.</hi> the other purpoſed betwixt M. <hi>I. Cr.</hi> and the ſame <hi>B. C.</hi> but diſappointed, it makes nothing at all for the taking away of Tithes, For as touching the former, they who were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153039:12"/>not poſſeſſed with prejudice, or corrupted with covetouſneſſe againſt the truth, were much confirmed in the lawfulneſſe of ſuch rates as are paid in <hi>London</hi> under the title of Tithes, though indeed they are not Tithes, and of ſuch onely was the debate at that time.</p>
               <p>For the intended debate which was to be touching the divine right of Tithes, though ſome godly and prudent men thought it ſhould not have been taken in hand without the warrant of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique authority, yet they made no doubt but that the truth of the cauſe, or ability of the man, who undertook the defence of it againſt M. <hi>C.</hi> would prevail unto victory. But for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment, it was by the warrant of the Lord Major of the City, to them both, interdicting the diſpute, which was both without M. <hi>I. Cr.</hi> his knowledge, and againſt his good will; yet he obeyed the prohibition, and when his Antagoniſt inſiſted, and urged the performance of what was agreed upon, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the contrary command of the Lord Major, his anſwer was, that it was agreeable to the Anabaptiſts principles to diſobey Authority, but not according to the principles of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians. And leſt <hi>B.C.</hi> ſhould take it for a token of diſtruſt in his cauſe, and make it an occaſion of vain-glory, either againſt the cauſe or perſon of M. <hi>I. Cr.</hi> he propoſed the printing of M. <hi>B. C.</hi> his arguments againſt Tithes, and engaged himſelf to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them in print, and ſo to refer both to the judgment of al un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed Readers, which was the beſt way to give clear and full ſatisfaction to ſuch as doubt on which ſide the truth is ſwayed by the moſt authentick teſtimony and ſoundeſt reaſons.</p>
               <p>It is no part of my task for the preſent to argue farther for Tithes, then may anſwer the doubt you have propoſed to me, which is, of the Parliaments purpoſe and proceedings touching the eſtabliſhing, or aboliſhing of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Animadverſions upon the late Pamphlet intituled,</hi> The Countreys plea againſt Tithes.</head>
               <p>YEt that you may not be ſcrupled in conſcience (as you were in conceit) by a new petty Pamphlet againſt payment of Tithes, which perhaps may come to your hands; I will give
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153039:13"/>you ſome animadverſions upon it; which may alſo be of uſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as well as to you. The title of the Booke is, <hi>The Countryes plea againſt Tithes,</hi> with this addition, <hi>A Declaration ſent to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers eminent Miniſters inſeverall pariſhes of this Kingdome, proving by Gods word and morall reaſon, that Tithes are not due to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell; and that the Law for Tithes was a Leviticall Law, and to endure no longer then the Leviticall Prieſthood did, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein the Authors ſay much in the outſide, but make no anſwerable proof in the inſide of the Booke. They direct it in the Title page as <hi>a Declaration to divers worthy Miniſters in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and in the beginning of the body of the Book they preſent it as <hi>a joynt Declaration of the people of ſeverall pariſhes for their opinion concerning Tithes,</hi> as a Reply <hi>to certaine papers from ſome Miniſters, pretending to prove Tithes due by authority of Scripture.</hi> It had been faire dealing if they had printed thoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Miniſters, that it might appeare how well they had anſwered them.</p>
               <p>But for the confident contradiction of the Divine right they alledge,
<list>
                     <item>1. The novelty of them in the Chriſtian ſtate.</item>
                     <item>2. The ceremoniality of them, as being meerely Leviticall.</item>
                     <item>3. The inequality of them in ſeverall reſpects.</item>
                     <item>4. The trouble of them to the Miniſter.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt; they referre the <hi>originall</hi> of them under the Goſpell, for the author, to Pope <hi>Vrbane;</hi> for the time, to the three hundredth yeare after Chriſts aſcenſion; and for proofe of both, they cite <hi>Origen, Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> at large without any particular quotation to find what they cite: <hi>untill which time,</hi> ſay they, <hi>there was community of all things among Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But firſt, they ſhould tell us which <hi>Vrban</hi> it was, (who they ſay began to bring Tithes into uſe for the maintenance of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) for there were 8 of that Name, and of thoſe 8 (if <hi>Origen</hi> be a witneſſe of it) it muſt be <hi>Vrban</hi> the firſt, Anno 227 who ſate but 6 yeares, &amp; 7 moneths, &amp; there was not another Pope called <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> untill the year 1087. which was long after the lateſt of thoſe three, <hi>viz. Gregory,</hi> (whether they mean <hi>Greg. Nazianz.</hi> or <hi>Greg. Nyſſen,</hi> or <hi>Gregory</hi> ſurnamed,) the <hi>Great,</hi> Biſhop of Rome; and <hi>Origen</hi> teſtified ſo much of Tithes recalled by Pope <hi>Vrban,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153039:13"/>their originall muſt be ancienter then 300 years after the aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for that <hi>Vrban</hi> lived not beyond the year 234, and <hi>Origen</hi> flouriſhed Anno 226. and if Tithes began when Chriſtians gave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the community of goods, as theſe men ſay p. 2. in the name of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> but bring no proofe of it, then had Miniſters a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in Tithes as ſoon as others had a propiety of eſtate; and ſooner it could not be. And that which cauſed this community, the perſecution of the Church (which reached to his age: <note place="margin">Tom. 1. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. p. 104.</note> for the next predeceſſor to that <hi>Vrban, Calixtus</hi> was a Martyr) might very well cauſe a ſuſpenſion of Tithes for all that time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>For the tenure of Tithes;</hi> there be 3 diſputable opinions: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Decimae ſunt pura eleemoſyna, &amp; parochiani poſſunt propter peccata ſuorum praelatorum, ad libitum ſuum auferreeas.</hi> Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Seſſion. 8. Tom. 7. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. p. 1016 col. 2. Artic. 18.</note> 1 Whether they be Morall; 2 whether Iudiciall; 3 whether Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, (there is a fourth conceipt that they are meere Almes, which is imputed to <hi>Wickleff</hi> in the 8 ſeſſion of the councell of Conſtance; but that admits of no diſpute ſince it is repugnant to all appearance of reaſon.) 1 Some hold them Morall, as thoſe Miniſters whom theſe men pretend to anſwer; moſt of the <hi>Caroniſts, Marc. Anton. de Dom. de Rep. Eccl. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Zepperus</hi> in <hi>Explic. legum forenſ. Moſ. c.</hi> 10. and many Engliſh Divines.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some hold them Judiciall, as <hi>Bell. lib de Cler. c.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Some Ceremoniall, as theſe pariſhioners doe. There is the leaſt reaſon for this laſt opinion. For Tithes were taken as a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute by God himſelfe as the chiefe Lord of all the earth, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. whereby hee is acknowledged giver of all; and that it is in his power to curſe the earth with barrenneſſe, and to ſtarve the creatures that live upon it; and this is true of all ages, and therefore we reade of payment of Tithes by <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 14.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.4. and vowing of Tithes by <hi>Jacob,</hi> before the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Prieſthood was eſtabliſhed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But ſacrifices, ſay they, are ancienter then Tithes, and were long before the Ceremoniall Law was ordained, yet they are not to be continued in the time of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> True, becauſe they were types of future things to be exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the New Teſtament, but Tithes have no typicall intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their inſtitution or uſe, being ſet apart by God for himſelfe, and given by him as the wages to his ſervants for doing his work; which he aſſigned to the <hi>Levites</hi> for their time, and made them ſutable to their ſtate by peculiar ordinances, as <hi>Num.</hi> 18.26, 27.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153039:14"/>&amp;c. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.3.4.5. which expired with the Prieſthood, though Tithes in generall did not; and therefore ſuch particulars are no more to be urged againſt that maintenance of Miniſters in the New Teſtament, then the Jewiſh obſervations of the Sabbath againſt the keeping of a Chriſtian Sabbath at this day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For that they ſay <hi>of inequality</hi> in reſpect of <hi>impropriations,</hi> p. 6. in reſpect of <hi>tradeſmen in Townes and Cities,</hi> who gaine more then farmers and pay no Tithes, p. 9. and in reſpect of the loſſe which may befall the farmer, when he hath not increaſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his coſt and labour, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the two firſt, it is worthy conſideration of thoſe who are in authority how to reduce them to more equality. For the third; the exception lyeth no more againſt Tithes now, then in the time when they acknowledge them moſt in force; and when it proveth an ill yeare with the plowman, it will be well for him to conſider whether his unconſcionableneſſe in Tithes have not procured a curſe upon his portion, according to the commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the third of <hi>Malac.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, for the <hi>trouble of the Miniſter;</hi> 1 If he have but a little Tithe, it will be no great trouble for him to order it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince he may lawfully exchange it into money. 2. If he have a great Tithe, it will beare the charge of a ſervant to eaſe him of the trouble. And 3. If this inconvenience could not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, (as well it may) there would follow farre greater upon the taking away Tithes, ſuch as before we have obſerved.</p>
               <p>With theſe exceptions againſt this revenue of Tithes they have delivered ſomething worthy the acceptation of Miniſters, which is p. 5.6. <hi>It is the deſire,</hi> ſay they, <hi>of al Gods people (&amp; ſo it ought to be) that the Miniſters of the Goſpell ſhould have a ſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance allowed them, nay not onely a ſufficient maintenance, but an abundant, a large and rich maintenance, ſuch a maintenance as they may live liberally without any other imployment but the Miniſtery; Nor is it fit or becomming Chriſtians that their Miniſter ſhould live in a meane condition either of diet or cloathing, but as he is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in calling, ſo ought he to have a more large &amp; better mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in thoſe reſpects then others, for he feeding the ſoules with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, the word of God, the people ought to feed his body libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally with their baſe temporall things:</hi> and in the next page ſay they;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153039:14"/>
                  <hi>And is it not a ſhame for a rich and flouriſhing common-wealth to have a poore and bare Miniſtery, either in the generall, or in ſome particulars? &amp; yet into ſuch a condition have Impropriations brought the Miniſtery of this common-wealth in very many places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They conclude with an addreſſe to the <hi>high court of Parliament for a reformation in this particular of Tithes,</hi> p. 10. and herein we are content to meet them at the barre of that moſt wiſe, pious, and impartiall Judicatory of the Kingdome, who, as they have, ſo we doubt not but they will ratifie the ancient Statutes, and their owne late Ordinance concerning Tithes; and whatſoever their title be in reſpect of religion, the people may (though ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant zelots hold, and covetous worldlings pretend they may not) pay them with good conſcience, for the State may impoſe them for the maintenance of the Miniſtery, as well as they may impoſe the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part, or any other part they pleaſe, to maintaine a juſt warre, or to pay the debts of the Kingdome; and others may conſcientiouſly ſubmit to ſuch impoſitions; and hereto the moſt learned Divines of the reformed Churches doe agree, (though the moſt of them, as they are miſtaken in the true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Sabbath, ſo are they alſo in this queſtion of Tithes) for albeit they maintaine their Miniſters while they live, and provide for their widowes and fatherleſſe children, when they are dead, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cujus legis (ſcil politicae) vi nec ipſi fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les reformati denegant ſolvere decimas, in reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis illas, in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſubjiciuntur Principibus qui illas lege ſolven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſanciunt; qua ratione eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am à theologis reſponſum fuit nonnullis qui ſcrupulo conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae ſe teneri praetendebant, ne pontificiis eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticis ſolve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent decimas, qui Idololatriae ſunt miniſtri.</hi> D. Rivet. Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. in Geneſ. Exercit. 80. p. 389. col. 2.</note> yet they reſolve it lawfull to pay the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſts, though they officiate in an Idolatrous ſervice, upon the command of the Prince, or State under which they live.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice for this little Treatiſe, which, though little, if it had not been leſſe in weight then in length, I would not have been ſo obſervant of the importunity of the Printers calling for my paper, as to diſpatch mine animadverſions upon it in the ſhort interim of one night, betwixt riſing from ſupper and repoſing for ſleepe, which yet had been too much if moſt readers were not too readily prepared to entertaine any Text that makes for their commodity, whether by acquiring advantage, or ſparing expences.</p>
               <p>Now for your ſecondary doubt concerning the diſpoſall of your ſonne, give me leave, Sir, to give you my ſence fully and freely in the caſe.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153039:15"/>
               <p n="1">1. I ſee by you and him (which I am ſorry to obſerve, yet I feare it is like to prove too true in all ages) that if there be not ſufficient and certaine meanes allotted to the labourers in the Lords harveſt, he is like to have but a few workemen to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it, and goe through with it; therefore thoſe that <hi>Julian</hi>-like, take away the hire of ſpirituall labourers, make way, as much as in them lyeth, for the marring of the harveſt; for either there will be a want of workemen, or of ſuch ſufficiency in them as may make the worke to proſper in their hands: hence is the miſerable condition of the Greeke Church, living (if not langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing) under the dominion of the Turkes, where their Clergy as they are the meaneſt ſort of men, (like <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Prieſts, who though they were to ſerve in the <hi>houſe of high places, were the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the people.</hi> 1 Kings 12.31.) ſo are they as deſpicable for their ignorance and meane qualifications every way as for their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, <note place="margin">G. Sandys his Travailes l. 1. p. 77.</note> having no ſchooles of learning among them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more like either to poiſon or famiſh the ſoules committed to their charge, then to feed and nouriſh them with a competent meaſure of <hi>the ſincere milke of the Word, that they may grow thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But I feare no ſuch fayling of maintenance for Miniſters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, as may occaſion ſuch a diſcouragement to parents that they ſhould not be willing to diſpoſe of their children in that calling, <note place="margin">Vincent. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>de</hi> Imag. Deor.</note> for feare they ſhould ſerve Chriſt upon ſuch poore termes as the Prieſts of <hi>Iſis</hi> did that heathen goddeſſe, who were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a new ſuite untill the old was worn to ragges.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet if that were true which you reade in the weekely pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, or which you had by report, of the likelyhood of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe Tithes by the Parliament, I muſt tell you plainly as your friend, I like not your wavering touching the diſpoſall of your ſonne; for if he be furniſhed with perſonall abilities for the ſervice of the Sanctuary, if he be (as I hope he is) a man of holy life and converſation, if he find himſelfe inwardly moved by the holy Ghoſt to enter into that holy function, it will be a greater ſacriledge in you then robbing of the Church of ſo much Tithe as would maintaine him, to divert him from the ſervice of Chriſt, and ſalvation of ſoules, through diſtruſt of the divine providence for his ſupport. And therefore,</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153039:15"/>
               <p n="4">4. If I conceived you to be ſo carnall a father (but I dare not thinke you are ſuch a one) I ſhould turne my ſpeech from you to your ſonne, had I opportunity to ſpeake with him, <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Licet in limine pater jaceat, per calcatum perge patrem ſiccis oculis ad vexillum cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis evola.</hi> Hic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. <hi>ad</hi> Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. Tom. 1. p. 2.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Genus pietatis eſt in hac re cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delem eſſe.</hi> Ibid.</p>
                  </note> and exhort him not onely to ſerve Chriſt, but to ſuffer for him, in the words of <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Heliodorus, rather to tread upon you, if you ſhould lye as a blocke in his way, then to make a ſtop, or to retire from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after Chriſt,</hi> though in zeale and haſte he ſhould overtake the Croſſe; for in ſuch a caſe <hi>it is a kind of piety</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ſhew cruelty towards our chiefeſt friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, as my little leiſure would allow me, I have endeavoured to ſatisfie your deſire in reſolving your doubt, and I hope that I have written will reach a little further then you thought of, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the ſettling of your reſolution to dedicate your ſonne to the ſervice of our Saviour; and to ſerve him upon ſuch tearmes whatſoever they be, as the Divine providence in the condition of the times ſhall put upon him, and ſo you have my advice, and you ſhall have my prayers for you and yours.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
